I'm Joe Hedzima. I'm going to be your guide on
our six-session journey through the nuts and bolts of new ventures.
Tonight at the beginning, I'm going to try to give you sort of a set of guideposts for you to
think about as you go into detail on all of the topics we're going to cover over the next six sessions.
And in that regard, I'm going to ask you a bunch of questions
that I want you to think about after every session that you come to,
because at the end, if you can answer those questions or at least
get closer to the answers, we'll have accomplished a whole bunch about your journey.
So the first question is, why are you here?
You know, it's a beautiful, warm night in Cambridge.
Wind chills in the single digits.
You know, why are you here?
I know it was for the three units
of credit you're going to get for the students.
You know, perhaps you don't know anything about
entrepreneurship, and you'd like to find out something.
You just want to dip your toe in the water.
So how many people here have
not taken a formal course in entrepreneurship?
Okay, there you go.
All right.
Including Bob back there.
So we're going to hopefully.
So this is a great environment for that.
It's a two-week period during January where
you don't have a lot of other distractions.
And hopefully we'll cover a lot of the
things that will tell you a lot about entrepreneurship.
Maybe you see something that sucks,
and you want to make it better.
Anybody have that?
Okay. Good.
Well, another student who had that was somebody who was
taking a bus back from New York City after Thanksgiving.
Back to campus.
And he forgot his USB drive,
and he couldn't get his files.
And he said, you know, I wasted the whole trip.
I want to figure out how I
can have those files anytime, anywhere I am.
And I said, well, you know, that's cloud storage, right?
That's Google Drive.
That's box.com.
And he said, yeah, but they really suck.
And I'm going to make something that doesn't suck.
He went on to found something called Dropbox.
And I've been using it ever since.
And it certainly doesn't suck.
It works quite well.
So maybe that's something that you want.
Maybe you have an idea or an invention, and you want to
bring it to life because you want to, like, change the world.
I think for most people that I run into
in entrepreneurship, that's sort of a primary driving factor.
They think they can make a big difference.
And that's, I think, a real driver for most people.
Of course.
Being an entrepreneur is glamorous, and
you can make a lot of money.
How many people like that one?
Okay, there's good, realistic people in the audience.
Well, we'll talk about that, too.
So many questions, regardless of why you're here.
So many questions you need to ask.
And we're going to try to
help you over the next six sessions.
How do I start?
What actually do I do?
What is the problem I'm solving?
Does my solution provide an answer to that problem?
Who cares about my idea?
Specifically, who cares?
Who's my customer?
And how do I find people, these people?
Bob Jones will be here in the second part of this
evening, and he's going to be talking a lot about that.
If you don't have a customer, you don't have anything.
How will I make money?
And make it?
That's the business model, or
the venture model, we call it.
And we'll be talking about that tomorrow.
How long will it take
to bring my solution to market?
What will it cost?
What resources will I need?
All of that stuff is about financial projections
and thinking through the model that you have.
Will I need to set up some sort of
entity to attract investors, other people to join me?
And what should it be?
Corporation?
Maybe a limited liability company?
And can I use that in any
way to provide some ownership incentive for people?
We'll be talking about that.
How do I keep people from stealing my idea?
You know, maybe you want to
put it out there for everyone.
But maybe you want to control a
little bit of how it gets used.
So we'll talk about, you know, can you
do it and how could you protect your idea?
Will I need co-founders?
And what will I rely on?
What will our relationship be?
Do we need some sort of an agreement?
Maybe a founder's agreement?
Tomorrow we'll have a panel on the founder's journey.
Some people that are in the midst of their journey.
You can ask that question to them too.
How will I negotiate with employees, consultants, whatever?
Entrepreneurs are always negotiating, right?
Because almost by definition you're trying to
assemble things you don't really own or control
to accomplish a vision you have.
So you've got to negotiate in some way
to bring on customers, to bring on people that
are going to join your team, advisors, and investors.
We'll have a session on negotiation.
And the big one, how do
I figure out what I don't know?
And, you know, one simple answer to that
is, well, maybe you find people that have done
it before who can advise you.
Reason I'm here and all the other presenters
are here is, well, I'm here to help you.
I'm here to help you.
And we've come down this path.
We have plenty of scars.
And we can perhaps tell you what
not to do or caution you on things.
What are the potholes in the road?
And how will I recognize them?
You know, you're gonna make mistakes.
If you don't, you're not doing it right.
The problem is not making a mistake.
It's making it twice, right?
So if you make a same
mistake twice, you haven't learned anything.
The problem in entrepreneurship really is, you know,
those things come at you in different clothing.
And there have been a number of cases when I've
been down the road and I go, oh, I recognize this.
I've been here before.
I didn't see it coming.
Can we give you some early warning things on that?
So there are a lot of moving pieces.
So the next question is, you know, why do this?
These are personal questions for you that you ought
to think about as you hear everything through the course.
Oh, did I miss one?
Oh, why do this?
Sorry.
What's the reward?
Fame?
Fortune?
You may recognize these people.
Some of them were
at the presidential inauguration yesterday.
Okay.
That may be the reward, but this is the reality.
This is how many people have heard of Nvidia?
Yeah.
Jason Wong, the founder, was interviewed and
he said he built a trillion dollar company.
You know, give or take a couple of billions.
That's what it's worth today.
Would he do it again?
He said, I don't think I would.
If I'd known three decades ago what
it would take, I wouldn't have done it.
This quote is amazing.
If we realize the pain, suffering, and how vulnerable
we are, we're going to be able to do it.
The challenges you're going to endure, the embarrassment and the shame and most of
all the things that could go wrong, nobody in their right mind would do it.
The embarrassment and the shame and most of all the things
that could go wrong, nobody in their right mind would do it.
So I must conclude from
that you guys are all crazy.
Right?
But this is a guy who
spent three decades to get there.
The reality is only 10% of startups succeed.
Nine out of ten fail.
Now, this includes everything from
sandwich shops and things like that.
Now, many of you are
interested in venture capital, I'm sure.
What do you think the
success rate is for venture capitalists?
Out of every ten companies they
invest, how many successes do they have?
Anybody?
One, I hear one.
Two?
Anybody else?
Well, the most successful
long-term firm was Kleiner Perkins.
And they got three successes for
every ten companies that they invested in.
Now, these are guys with money, smarts.
With venture capitalists, you've got to realize
they're always the smartest people in the room.
Make sure you understand that.
They'll let you know.
And connections.
And with all of that, they only
win three out of every ten times.
Can you think of any other thing you could do where
if you failed seven times out of ten, you'd be a hero?
Baseball.
Baseball, right.
If you bat 300, you're probably leading the league.
And you're probably making, what do they
make now, 50, 100 million a year?
So if you really want
to make money, go play baseball.
But the point is, success is only 10% in general.
Now, there are many reasons.
When you look into them, I want to
focus on the one in the bottom right,
which says 99% of the time people fail.
By the way, these slides will all
be available, but feel free to take pictures.
99% fail because of a lack of planning and experience.
We're going to try to
help you on the planning part.
And with that, you'll get experience.
But even though 10% is a success rate,
maybe all is not.
And that's not dismal.
We're here at MIT.
The Kauffman Report.
MIT is known for entrepreneurship around the world.
Kauffman Report, in 2009, studied
the roughly 26,000 active companies
that were founded by MIT alum or faculty.
Now, that's out of 120,000 living alums at the time.
So that's like one of
every five that were out there.
These companies employed three.
They had annual revenues of $2 trillion a year.
And if you put them together as a single country,
it would be the largest,
11th largest economy in the world.
Now, does that mean we're better at success here?
I don't know.
But it might mean that when we do succeed,
there are much bigger successes.
With these statistics, people come from all over the world
to try to figure out what they're doing.
And they're not.
They're not.
And so I'll give you a
little hint about some of the things
that can help on that.
OK, so why this course, after all of that?
Well, this course is not about theory.
It's about doing.
The people that are going to
be talking to you are not academics
studying entrepreneurship.
Every single one of them either are actively doing,
or have done, what they're going to talk about.
And it goes back to sort
of the beginning of the course.
I was teaching a course on, which is now
called Law for Entrepreneurs.
And some students came up and said,
you know, you have some very practical things
that you talk about.
Could you do a course during January independent activities
period on how to start a company?
And I said, oh, you know, I'll think about it.
Well, this is pre-internet, believe it or not.
They went and somehow got the course in the catalog.
And they called me up and
said, we put it in the catalog,
and we dare you not to show up.
I said, boy, that's pretty gutsy.
I was a little annoyed at that.
But then I said, you know, there's something here.
These are like customers.
These are people that want what they
think I can deliver to them.
They actually want it.
I'm not looking for them.
They came to me.
So how am I going to do that?
I didn't have time.
I didn't have time to really plan anything out.
So at the time, we had four nights.
And I thought, well, what are
sort of two things a night
that we could talk about?
And I got on the phone, and I called people.
And some I knew, and some I didn't.
I knew all the people I called.
Some of them I said, could you come and talk
to a group of people at MIT, students,
about whatever the topic is?
And to make it easy, just come and say,
I wish.
The three or four or five whatever things
that I wish somebody had told me about the area
that I'm going to talk about when I started up.
And then we'll just open it up for questions.
Now, about half the people that ended up showing
that came to present, I didn't know personally.
But I had people that I called and said,
do you know anyone who could do this?
And they've got to be able to keep it simple.
And then because I was worried that I
was going to get all these people in the audience,
or these presenters to come, I said,
I've got to have some people in the audience.
So I called everyone else I knew.
And we packed a room with 120 people.
And people were sitting in the aisles.
And it was a real good lesson for me.
It was a great success.
And it was a real lesson.
Because what I did is
I basically said, here's the goal.
Here's what we want to do.
I found good people.
I gave them an idea of what to talk about,
or what I wanted them to talk about.
And then I got out of the way.
And they did a fantastic job.
And we sort of refined that model over the years.
So it's really about doing.
We call it New Ventures.
It's planning and executing new ventures.
That could be business.
It could be nonprofit.
It could even be government.
One year, we had the
US Mint show up for class.
They were thinking of launching some new thing.
And they wanted to come and see about new ventures.
And by the way, it's the Sloan
School of Management.
It's not the Sloan School of Business.
So that's in our DNA.
Our goal is to increase the probability
that you'll be in the 10%.
That's what we're trying to do.
Now, you have to recognize that entrepreneurship
is a lifetime incurable disease.
If you get it, you will have
it for the rest of your life.
Fortunately, it's not fatal in most cases.
It's highly recommended.
It's highly contagious.
And it's transformative.
But what it really is
also is a full contact sport.
So it's, again, not about theory.
It's about getting out there and doing things.
And again, the people that are going to be talking
are doing or have done what's involved.
So let me give you an overview of the specifics
we're going to cover and what you can learn
during the six sessions.
First, how to evaluate a venture from an impact
and economic viewpoint.
This is really a key thing.
What is the scarcest resource you have?
Time.
And if you're planning to do a new venture,
you saw that Nvidia took three decades.
It's not going to be a six-month thing.
And if you're going to
spend your time and effort working
on something, you want to might think at the beginning,
do I think this is going to work?
Is this going to have impact?
How do I do that?
Because it's your time that you're
burning up if you do that.
We had a, I used to
do a seminar on Tuesday nights.
And I know we have some people from Harvard here.
So I don't mean to disparage people from Harvard.
But one night, this is a seminar with 12 people.
And one night, three people show up
from Harvard Business School.
And we were an open seminar.
I said, well, great.
Well, tell us, why are you here?
What are you looking for?
And they said, well, we're taking an entrepreneurship course
at the business school.
OK.
And we have to start a company.
Excuse me?
You have to start a company.
Yeah, yeah, we've got to start a company.
Well, what is that?
You've got to learn how to incorporate?
No, no, we actually have to start something.
And I said, that's really stupid.
If we spend four months with you looking at something
and you realize this is something you shouldn't do,
it means you're going to fail the course.
And they said, I don't know.
We're supposed to start a company.
The point is, figuring out
what to do and figuring out
what not to do are a key part of entrepreneurship.
OK, so we're also going
to figure out who's your customer.
How do I get financial resources for the venture?
How do I scale it and make it sustainable?
How do I build and retain a top-notch team
of both internal and external people?
How do I negotiate deals and resolve team conflicts?
What are the legal pitfalls?
And how do I pitch my venture idea?
And Bob is going to come.
Bob Jones will be back
to talk about pitching your venture.
And it's not only to investors.
It's to all the people you need to convince
to join you in whatever journey you're taking.
So there are a lot of moving pieces here.
These personal questions, these are
things you need to think about.
Do you really want to do this?
Right?
Should you do it?
No.
Why?
And should you do it now or later?
If you're an MIT student now,
you know how hard MIT is
and how you're getting by on meager resources
and your diet probably isn't the best in the world.
Probably a good time to start a company because you
won't notice a difference.
10 years later, you're married with children,
a whole different scenario.
And is this for me?
So if you look at each of the sessions,
we dig down into the nuts and bolts.
Think about these.
And by the end, think about, personally, what
does this mean for you?
OK, so what's tonight's plan?
We're going to talk about who you are.
We're going to introduce the teaching team.
I'm going to give you an overview of frameworks.
I hate frameworks.
I'm going to give you some
things to think about to help
you digest the stuff you're
going to see in the future.
Then we're going to do a break for team building.
And we'll talk about that.
And then Bob will be back.
He'll be back with his magnifying glass looking for,
or binoculars looking for customers.
So who are you?
Well, your students from all of these different departments.
The first time we opened this up for credit,
we didn't know who was in the audience.
And it was really interesting.
We had a clump of people
over there and a clump of people
over there.
And I said, and I'll do
it tonight, how many people from,
from Sloan? Okay. How many people
from science and engineering? Good, all right.
You've done better than the first class
because all the Sloan people were there
and the science and engineering people were
over there and so I said to the
Sloan people, look at the number on your seat.
If it's an odd number, get up and go
find an odd number and, you know,
switch because we wanted to bring people
together. And then I'm thinking, God,
how's this gonna work? The Sloan people
probably know everything I'm going to talk
about so I'm gonna bore them to
death. And the science and engineering people,
this is all brand new and they're
really smart but, you know, am I gonna overload
them? But I had what I had and I
just went forward and it turned out
to work well because the things we were
talking about were very practical things. So
the range of people here, these are
the interest groups that if you signed
up on the email list that people were
interested in. We'll talk about that
at the break. We also have non-student
participants. We have alums,
some people that have done numerous
companies successfully and are back. We
have, I think, some MIT Venture Mentoring
Service people in the audience. We have
people, I think we have a faculty
member or two. We have people from large
companies who are looking to spin out
something. This all came from when you
when you signed up on the email list,
what are you looking to get out of the
course. So the question is how do we deal
with all of that? Well it's MIT so we
have to have an equation. H equals R
divided by E. The goal is to maximize H.
H is happiness. I know a couple
of people have taken the course before.
Don't answer the question. What is
R and what is E? R? Reality?
Okay well typically maybe this is good.
Reality is the thing. The first time I
did this the Sloan people said oh it's
very easy. It's revenue is R and expenses
are E.
And I said yeah that's great but that's
a subset of this equation. So R is
reality. What is E? Expectations. Okay
so you're happy if reality exceeds your
expectations. Right? If you under promise and
over deliver are people happy? If you
over promise and under deliver are they happy?
Not as much. Right? So this is
a universal principle. Happiness is reality divided
by expectations. Now I'm tempted to say
I can make you infinitely happy if you
just stop having any expectations for
this course. You have zero expectations
you're going to be happy. But I
know that's not possible because on that
email list the things you wanted to know
about that E is very high and we're
going to try to deliver the R and I hope that
the E is very high. So it's about to be a happy.
We'll come back to that and do a poll at
the end. Okay so who are we? Again we are
highly unpaid volunteers who have done this and
I hate to say it but the TAs are
the only people getting paid in this
course and for them it's nothing. It's
like a couple of lattes right? And now
why would these people come and and spend
cold nights in January to talk about this
stuff and not get paid for it? Well
we're going to have some mugs
or something but other than that. Well
because I think if you ask
entrepreneurs who have been successful especially one
successful and you really got them in
a quiet moment with a couple beers or
whatever and they'd say you know I
couldn't have gotten here without a lot
of help and people helped me along the
way and I want to help the next
generation coming by. And I think that's really
true there's a real give back in
the entrepreneurial era and you know when
you guys succeed please make
sure you're mentoring and helping entrepreneurs
after you. So a little bit about me.
I've done a bunch of ventures everything from
being the lawyer, co-founder, investor,
board member, advisor, a bunch of
different companies. I'll talk about several
of them when a little bit later.
I was I've been a lecturer
at Sloan for a long time.
I was a partner at Sullivan & Worcester,
a big law firm in Boston. I founded their
high-tech new ventures group. I was
chairman emeritus at the MIT Enterprise
Forum which no longer exists in its
current form but it had 20 some odd
chapters all over the world. A
director at Main Street Partners that
commercializes technology and I'm
currently working on two companies.
IP Vision which is an intellectual property analysis.
I'm a firm and Neuro Sim
Technologies which is making low-cost medical devices.
Now the most important people you need to
know are TAs. Janet, hands up. She's a
2026 Sloan candidate. Deloitte Consulting before
that in Media and Tech. Psychobiology.
I don't want to mess with you. And
head of operations at the MIT 100k competition.
There's a big connection between the 100k
competition in this class. The class was
actually formed to see if we
could help people entering the competition have
more of an understanding of what a
venture was and not what I guess ideas
were. So tomorrow night Janet and Supriya
will present a little bit about the
100k. Hopefully you'll be interested in it.
Supriya? Yep. 2026 also. A software
engineer at Amazon Web Services and Gaming.
That's good. Was a Fulbright Nehru scholar
and co-founded a company there and she's
the incoming managing director of the
100k competition. So you've probably already been
in contact with them on a lot of
logistical questions and they've done a great job so
far. If they don't let me know and I'll,
don't tell me, tell them. Okay. I'll introduce the
presenters when they present going forward.
Okay. So I'm going to introduce the
presenters. I'm going to introduce the presenters. I'm
going to introduce the presenters. I'm going to
introduce the presenters. I'm going to introduce the
presenters. I'm going to introduce the
presentations. Please let me speak. And, you
know, using a 70%嘉 يعys DB is
an excellent way to support business
expectations quite a lot of work,
particularly if you are an entrepreneur. But I
wanted to give you a little bit more
of a background for what I'm going to
talk about in just a minute. A, is it
not right, is it very important that there date to
make investments with a very short yet АннуAy,
period.
expenditure in the market.
the answers are not.
That's the real key.
If you know what questions to ask,
finding the answers is hard.
But if you do that correctly, you'll be a success.
So what do you need for success?
Well, the first thing you do
is you have to create value.
Because if you don't create value,
you don't have anything, right?
Now, there's a lot behind that.
Like, what kind of value?
For whom am I creating the value?
How much value do I create?
What does it cost me to create that value?
How often do people want that value?
A lot of things.
We're going to talk about all that stuff.
So create value.
But if you create value and that's it,
you don't have a successful venture
because you've got to capture some of that value
so you can do it again.
In the for-profit world,
that's eventually profit and cash flow.
In the not-for-profit world,
it can be creating enough interest
that you can get other people to give you resources.
It's the model that you're going to create
that will allow you to
capture some value that you create.
Real simple.
Create value, harvest value.
So that's one way to think about
the things you're going to look at
during the six sessions.
Now, another way to look at it
is what I've called the three whys.
I've looked at probably several thousand
business plans over the years and heard pitches.
And I've talked to investors
about what they're looking for.
And I've talked to founders and other things.
And I think it boils
down to three basic why questions.
The first is, why this?
Why is this idea that you're telling me about
worth doing or investing in?
Why?
Is it the size of the market?
Is it a problem worth solving?
Amy Smith entered the 100K competition
probably, I don't know, 15 years ago.
And she was at the Edgerton Center.
Amy was big on the developing world.
And D-Lab, I think, was part of what she did.
And she got into the finals of the 100K.
And she got up on Kresge at the big auditorium.
And I remember her pitch.
It went like this.
She said, 1.9 billion people on the planet
don't have access to clean water.
I mean, I was clueless.
You're kidding me.
1.9 billion people?
That's a big problem.
The only way to test for biological contamination
is to incubate a sample of water.
The only incubators in the market today
are powered by electricity.
The 1.9 billion people that don't have access
to clean water, by and
large, don't have access to electricity.
I've got an incubator that doesn't require electricity.
Would you like to hear more?
Big problem, right?
Now, that's something I can get behind.
She went on and did a bunch of things.
Eventually won a MacArthur Genius Award.
I haven't talked to her in several years.
I hope she's all right.
But it was so riveting, her presentation.
So why this?
Why is this a big idea?
Why is this worth spending your time?
Or if you're an investor, why
would I put my money behind you?
Or if you're trying to
get me to come on board
and be part of your team, why
would I want to join the team?
Why this?
The second why.
Why now?
Why is now the right time to do this?
Well, sometimes it can be the convergence
of opportunity and solution.
So one of the contestants in
the 100K back in the day,
had an elegant plan for fixing the defects in
the air traffic control system in the United States.
I mean, it was really quite well done.
And the judges were there saying,
well, that's all fine and good, but you know,
you can't just fix part of it.
You've got to fix the whole system.
And they looked at us and they said,
well, didn't you know that the FAA has put out
a request for proposal for a new air traffic control system?
No, you didn't tell us that.
Well, now we have a timing.
Why now?
Somebody wants this now and we've got the solution.
If they'd had that solution five years before
or after the new system was put in place,
even though it's a great idea,
it may not be the right time to do it.
So why this?
Why now?
The third why.
Why this team?
Why do I think these people will win?
Great idea.
Good timing.
Why these people?
Well,
you know,
it could be prior experience.
Although that doesn't always count.
There was a company back in my
law days that I represented called Encore Computer.
And Encore was founded by the
technical founders of Digital Equipment Corporation,
Prime Computer,
and Data General.
The three biggest mini computer
companies at the time got together
and they were going to
make a new generation of computers.
Prior experience, out of the park amount.
Did it succeed?
No.
Bunch of issues there.
But prior experience got them funded.
But if you're a starting entrepreneur
and you don't have prior experience,
how do you show that this team is right?
Well, it could be a compelling model you have.
It could be the people you attract around you.
Okay?
So why now?
Why this?
Why now?
Why this team?
And then the fourth question that comes up.
Why won't this work?
Now, salespeople will tell you when the
prospect starts asking you a bunch of questions
about the limits of the thing you're trying to sell,
they know they've got you on a hook.
Because you're interested.
You're trying to test it out.
So this fourth one is if
you don't get through the first three,
you won't get to the fourth.
This is where you've got to start thinking
about what are the risks in what I'm doing
and how do I de-risk it?
How do I anticipate things?
What's my plan B?
So that's another way to think about it.
So we had the first concept, create value, capture value.
The three why concepts for you to
think about as you look at ventures.
Now I'm going to do some lesson
learned from things that I actually worked on
that would hopefully give you some
ideas about how to look at things.
And there are four critical components
that I've distilled from thinking about
all the things I've worked on over the years.
There are ideas.
You need all of these components together.
You need ideas.
You need to be able to execute.
You have to get the timing right.
And you've got to get the people right.
And if you do all of that,
that's probably your 10% success right there.
And maybe it's bigger.
But if you don't get all of those things aligned,
you're going to have a hard time.
So let's look at it
in a little bit more detail.
Ideas.
You've got to have something.
But ideas are a dime a dozen.
That's an expression people use.
Around MIT, there are ideas all over the place.
Everything from genomics to AI to
nanotechnology to latest drug type stuff.
They're all over the place.
The question is, is it a valuable
idea or can it be made valuable?
And the question is, to whom?
Is this idea valuable?
And how much value?
This is, again, riffing on that create value concept.
And then finally, is it easily copied?
Because if I have a great
idea, but anyone can do it,
that may be still something you want to do.
Maybe that's open source stuff,
but you can't build a venture around that very well.
So you have to have some good ideas.
The second component, execution.
Thomas Edison.
Vision without execution is hallucination.
Now Edison, the modern day Edison, Dyson,
spent how many experiments did they
run to try to figure out?
In Edison's case, it was trying to find
a filament that would work as a light bulb,
and eventually it was bamboo, of all things.
And Dyson, I don't know what it is,
but he talked about finding a light bulb.
He talked about finding the
10,000 ways things didn't happen.
But execution on that idea is key.
I'm going to tell you about
two deals that I passed on
because I had concerns about their execution.
The first is Zipcar.
People have heard of Zipcar?
Okay, so Zipcar was the concept that
I don't need to own a car.
If I want to get from here to there,
there's a lot of things I can do.
I can own a car.
I can get a cab.
I can rent a car
for a day or a week.
But what if I could rent
a car for an hour or two?
That's a fundamental break in how transportation is done.
And they came in and they talked and I said,
well, tell me about it.
Oh, we're going to have this thing.
We're going to have an app and you'll see
a car in a parking space on the 6th Street.
You'll swipe it.
You'll do this and then you
can do it and take it back.
It's going to work.
It's going to work that way.
I said, okay.
Well, where are you going to start?
Oh, we're going to start in Cambridge.
I said, in Cambridge?
They said, you clearly don't know
the story about recruiting faculty in Cambridge
where they say to the faculty, the would-be faculty member,
I'm going to give you three things.
You can pick one of them.
We can give you tenure.
We can give you the Nobel Prize.
Or we can give you parking.
And the smart ones say, I'll take
the parking because if I have parking,
I can get to work and I can figure
out how to get tenure and the Nobel Prize.
Parking is a big deal in Cambridge.
And if you've got to do that in
every single city, that's a major execution thing.
I don't understand how you're going to do it.
And I said, you know, I wish you well, but
I'm just not going to be on that journey with you.
Now, it turned out they
did eventually, I think, go public.
It was a hard slog.
The founders might have felt good that
they changed a fundamental part of transportation.
But in terms of their personal economic reward, it
wasn't very much at the end of the day.
But that's okay if I go back to the questions
of what am I looking for, if that works for you.
But it didn't work for me
just to join them on that journey.
The second one was a precursor to eBay.
It wasn't eBay, but the same
concept that I saw before eBay.
And I listened to them and I said, okay,
let me see if I can boil this down.
I'm going to buy something sight unseen from somebody
I've never met and nobody standing behind the transaction.
Boy, that sounds like it
could be a fraught with fraud.
You know, I don't quite figure
out how you're going to do it.
And so I'm going to pass on it.
Well, eBay itself got going.
And there's a great story about how, you know, Pez
dispensers and all that stuff, if you read about it.
And eventually, you know, they did have fraud.
They did figure out how to get insurance.
But the point is there were a lot of
execution things that were very difficult for me to understand.
And I didn't think that I
could help them on that journey.
So that was two examples of execution issues.
Now, MIT, this is right at
the heart of MIT, ideas plus execution.
The motto of MIT is
mens et manus, mind and hands.
So this is, you know, not unknown that
you need ideas and you need to execute.
But those two are not, they're necessary, but they're not
sufficient for success because you need the other two pieces.
And timing.
I've lost more money and
time being ahead of the curve.
This is a quote from somebody you know.
Me.
Fortunately, I've been able to do it.
I've been able to catch some
waves and I've done all right.
I'm not complaining.
But I've crashed and burned a lot of the times
because I was ahead of the curve in thinking about stuff.
It can take, this is especially for technology ventures, it
can take a long time to be an overnight success.
NVIDIA, three decades.
3D printing, over 25 years.
The last night of the course, Marina had something.
She's going to come and talk about
some things that she's learned over the years.
She was one of the founders of ZCorp,
which was one of the first 3D printing companies.
And a couple years ago, I was at an investment conference and
someone came up and said, you know, you do stuff at MIT.
Yeah, yeah, I do.
I said, tell me about this new 3D printing.
And I said, it's not new.
The patents have expired.
The original patents.
And what has happened is in the last few years, there have been advances in material science, in sensor technology, and in microelectronics
that have now made some of this stuff work beyond the simple area of 3D printing so we can do more broader things.
The point is, it took a number of years for all the ancillary pieces
of technology to come together to really make 3D printing what it is today.
And it's even, the jury's
out whether it's really that successful.
There have been, if you follow the news on this, there have been a
lot of strain among some of the 3D printing companies that have gone public.
Another example is Prodigy.
I doubt any of you have heard of Prodigy.
Anybody?
Oh, a couple of historians here.
Well, Prodigy was a joint venture.
It was one of the first sort of online things.
It was a joint venture
between CompuServe and Sears and Roebuck.
And one of the things they were going to
do was they were going to do on your computer.
It was a computer.
They were going to be
able to go online and shop.
And back then, you know, they didn't have,
the browsers weren't anywhere near what they are today.
They spent more than a billion dollars
trying to get that concept off the ground.
And that's what a billion dollars was, real money.
I guess it's still real money.
But today, how many people have bought
something at Amazon and don't raise your hand.
I know you all have in the last month.
That's here today.
So, it's a good time for that to happen.
The other one, and this has
a double meaning on it, is fusion.
People have been working on fusion
for generating electricity for 50 plus years.
Now, recently there have been some
advances, or at least people investing.
There's Commonwealth Fusion here in Massachusetts backed
big bucks by people like Bill Gates, etc.
One of the problems with something like
fusion, and I call it my fusion problem,
is fusion doesn't work unless all of it works.
You can't, it's not like 3D printing when you can make
a little thing and do a little prototyping with a 3D printer.
It either works or it doesn't.
And if you're going down and looking at a
venture that requires all of the pieces to come together,
that's a risky proposition.
And things like fusion, that's where
the government long-term investment should be,
you know, to provide the
stability to build out those technologies.
So timing is important.
And then finally, people.
People are the single biggest source of
failure in most ventures, in my experience.
Here's a quote from Alice in Wonderland.
One day Alice came to a fork in the
road and saw a Cheshire cat in a tree.
Which road do I take? she asked.
Where do you want to go? said the cat.
Alice answered, I don't know.
And the cat said, well, then it doesn't really matter.
Right?
And what happens, let's say we decide that we're going
to go watch the New England Patriots play football next week.
Well, wait a second, there
are a couple problems with that.
First of all, they've had a terrible
season and they're not playing next week.
So what if we want to go see the Celtics?
All right, it's a pretty good team.
So we agree we're going to go see the Celtics.
And we start off.
And we had a road closed sign.
In Boston, there are two seasons, winter and construction.
And recently, they seem to be the same season.
But if we go to that road closure
sign, we know where we want to go.
We'll figure out how to get there.
We might have to take a big,
long, more expensive way to get there.
But as a team, we'll figure it out.
A number of years ago, I had three MIT teams come
into my office when I was practicing law, which was great.
And they had some great ideas.
And the first one came in,
and there were three of them.
And the first person, I said,
tell me one of your goals.
What are your goals for this venture?
The first one said, I want this
technology to be a standard in the industry.
Oh, that's a pretty good goal.
How about you?
The next person, oh, this is really big.
I want to grow it and take it public.
We can make a lot of money.
Well, that's a good idea, too.
What about the third person?
Well, I think it's important.
But I think we should be a collegial group.
And we can make money, but
we don't have to grow like gangbusters.
I don't want to call it lifestyle,
but I don't want to go crazy.
And I sort of put my pen down.
I was writing.
And I said, did you
three just meet in the elevator?
I mean, think about it.
The one who wants the technology to be
standard might want it to be open source.
Give it away.
I want it everywhere.
The person who wants to go public wouldn't want that to
happen unless they can figure out an open source model, right?
Because I want to grow something fast and valuable.
And the third person, I don't know where they are.
But when they hit their first bump in the
road, what do you think is going to happen?
And it doesn't matter if
you don't know where you're going.
So maybe I've overblown it.
But it was so stark.
I really said, did you just meet in the elevator?
Well, I said, no.
I'm going to go back to the elevator.
OK.
Other people-related issues.
This doesn't happen too often.
But when venture money is a lot of money chasing deals out there,
and there are hot periods of time, AI is part of that now,
you may get funded before
you really understand what you're doing.
And an example, sort of an analogy example, is suppose
your idea was you think people want to watch football.
So you assemble a football
team and you buy a stadium.
And then you go out to start to sell tickets.
And what happens?
People say, I want to watch basketball.
It's cold out there.
I don't want to go football.
Now you've got a situation where you've invested all
this time and money with people, football players, great athletes.
But they don't really play basketball
the way that a basketball player would.
And now you've got an internal pivot.
Instead of looking at the
customer, you've got this internal pivot.
You've got this internal conflict.
Like who's going to get fired?
We've got to change the model.
I mean, it just starts
to disintegrate all over the place.
And then not knowing what you don't know.
So E-Ink came out of
the media lab here at MIT.
It was the ability to make a low-cost, at the
time, black and white display that would display things electronically.
Eventually, it ended up as the original Kindle reader.
And they came in, and they really
knew what they were going to do.
They were all going, oh, we're going
to do this, that, and the other thing.
And we listened to them, asked them questions,
and we're thinking, I don't know about these guys.
How much do you think you're
going to take to get there?
Oh, $15 million.
That's going to be more than enough.
And I remember saying, I don't see how you're
going to do it for less than $80 million.
And I was off by $80 million.
Eventually, they raised $160 million.
And they eventually got it out.
But they were so sure they knew everything that
they were doing, they didn't know what they didn't know.
And again, we didn't want to partner up with people that don't
know that they don't know stuff and want to learn about it.
So now, this is a curve graph.
You'll see it later, maybe this week.
In the 100K competition, we bring together people.
And after a few years, we realized that
some of the teams were having a hard time.
And we realized that some of
the teams were having a hard time.
And we realized that some of the
teams were having internal problems and blowing up.
And typically, there would be a
technical founder and then a business founder.
And they would try to figure out what they're doing.
And as I listened to all the cases of all
the problems they were having, I came up with this graph.
And the vertical axis is relative importance.
And the horizontal axis is time.
And if I have a technical founder whose idea it is, his or her idea,
working maybe in the lab, working 60, 70, 80 hours a week, just like crazy.
The business founder at the beginning may be working on another regular job, working on
this in the evenings and weekends, trying to figure out the market and all that stuff.
But until we have something that
works technically, we don't have a business.
And now it comes to have
a discussion about who's our business.
And now it comes to have a discussion about how
we're going to split up the equity in the company.
Where would you put the technical entrepreneur's
view of the world at the beginning?
Pretty high.
What do you think the technical person
is going to think about the business person?
Pretty low.
Now, how do you build a team around that?
What happens over time?
The relative importance of the technology goes down.
The relative importance of the business side goes up.
Whether they cross or not doesn't matter.
But when I put this graph together and they realize, you know, it really takes a team to make
this work, it began to open up a whole level of discussions about, you know, how do we structure ourselves?
How is it going to work?
A classic people issue.
Happens, of course, with
technology companies more than others.
Okay.
So there's what we're trying to get at.
Now, I'm going to give you a four-part question.
Now, I'm going to give you four actual companies I worked with, and I'm going
to talk about how these came together or didn't and what we can learn from them.
The first I'll call SpeechCo.
This had all of the four components.
It went public.
And basically, if you have Siri on
your phone, that's where Siri came from.
DARPA, the Defense Advanced Research Project Agency,
is a very good example of that.
It's a very good example of that.
I mean, Google did a really good
job of communicating with these three party systems.
Here, if you want to have slides that show who people are and
what they're up to, their code, you guys should use way fewer survivors時
So Speech-PCómo-Co, that way people were
introduced and familiar with the people better.
That's all you need.
ciento
Well, so one part of that
was, I don't seem to recognize race.
It came in two parts.
Why did it come in two?
words mean? Now, this is before we've had the
advances in AI that we've had today, but that's
sort of, you can see the beginning of it.
So the technical founder came out of Victor Zhu's lab
here at MIT and came to me and
we started talking about this concept. And he said,
you know, we can do this now
in telephony. We can do telephone systems,
spark workstations, have the power. We don't
need mainframes. We can make this work.
At the same time, there was a client
of mine who had just sold his business to
Adobe and was on a one-year sort
of earn out, work out, non-compete type thing.
So I put the two of them together
and the three of us spent that year
having endless meetings, Chinese food dinners,
talking about how could this all work.
Because the business guy couldn't really work
on it yet because he was still working
at Adobe.
By the way, I could usually figure out
when a former client would, after they sold their
business, would be back. I could almost put it on
my calendar a year and a day after the deal
closed, they'd be back wanting to do something else.
So we went out, you know, spent all that
time planning and thinking about it. They went out
and we raised money from, you know, a venture
firm. There's a whole history of, if you
haven't studied it, in the world of speech recognition
about some fraud that was done by a company.
And I think that's a really good example of that.
But the thing that went on that these guys managed
to avoid, they went public and it worked out just fine.
And the reason is the idea was great. The
timing was perfect because the compute power was there.
The execution, back then, because of the way
AI, you know, we didn't have the power.
If you were going to do this, you normally
wanted to do it in a domain of knowledge.
And so you would learn from
how people spoke in that domain.
So they managed to figure out how
to do a deal with Eastern Airlines,
which was one of the big
airplane carriers back in the day.
And Eastern thought this was great, that they
could do online or, you know, over phone
reservations. But they didn't want
to expose their customers to it.
So they said, can you
do this for our flight crews?
So when you're a flight crew on a thing, you need
to figure out how to shuttle back to your home or whatever.
And so they set it up and the flight crews were the
ones that tested the system and they learned the domain around it
and how to deal with it. You know,
I need to be in Cleveland on Tuesday.
You know, obviously they wanted to fly. They weren't
going to be renting a car or something like that.
So the execution was great. And the people, because
of that year they spent getting to know each other,
they worked well, very well
together. So that was a success.
The second one is also a success.
I'll call it VideoCo, although I'm going
to show you the name in a moment.
This was somebody out of Sloan,
technology out of the Media Lab.
It was desktop video editing on the Macintosh computer.
At the time, if you were going to do video
editing, the equipment was like a million dollars kind of equipment.
Usually you'd go to a video editing
studio and you'd spend a day there.
And they said, you know, the technology is
such now, even though the Mac wasn't the best,
the most powerful computer, that we can
actually do video editing on a desktop machine.
So the idea was good.
The timing was good because
of the technology that was there.
The execution had me worried at the beginning.
So the name of the company when
they incorporated it was Macromedia Business Applications Corporation.
And in short order, they
got a letter from the company.
They got a letter from Macromedia, a bigger
company, saying, hey, wait a second, that's our name.
And, you know, trademark infringement, we're
going to get you and everything.
And it turned out our guys used
the word, the term before Macromedia did.
So Macromedia, the big company, said,
well, can we buy out the name?
So they said, here's $25,000.
All you have to do is
change the name of your company.
Hey, good way, non-delutive equity, non-equity funding.
So I got the check.
All they have to do is file something at
the state that says change the name to anything.
And two weeks go by, and I'm calling.
I said, what's wrong with you guys?
Just give me any name.
I don't care what.
They said, well, you know, we
found some really cheap space in Cambridge.
Why don't you come over, and
we'll show you what we're doing.
So I go over there, and
they have a whiteboard covered with names.
And I'm going, oh, God, these guys.
They can't pick a name.
How are they going to execute on anything?
So what they did, eventually, this is
the name that they came up with.
Digital Video Applications Corp.
And they shortened it to DIVA.
Two years later, the largest
video editing company acquired them.
The name of that company?
Avid.
Here's how Avid is spelled.
They weren't picking a name.
They were picking a strategy.
Right?
DIVA is Avid spelled backwards.
It focused everything they did.
We went to the closing,
and they gave me a T-shirt.
They said, I know you didn't
think we could execute very well.
They gave me a T-shirt in
the front that said DIVA from home.
And the back said Avid to Hollywood.
So an example of a company that
I had doubts about on the execution.
The people part worked out well.
Okay, now some stories that didn't work out.
I'll call this one HIV Co.
This was back when AIDS
was just hitting a big epidemic.
The two co-founders were the discoverers of the CD4.
Which is the main receptor
as part of the immune system.
They got funded by some very big Wall Street people.
Names you would know if I told you.
They had a science advisory
board that included Anthony Fauci.
That's when I first met him.
And a couple of other people, but
two very notable people at the time.
Luc Montigny from Institute Pasteur and Robert
Gallo from the National Institutes of Health.
In public,
these two,
had disputes going as to about who first discovered HIV.
Enough so that eventually President Reagan and President
Chirac of France had to resolve the issue.
But on that science advisory board, they
were very collegial and they got things done.
So what went wrong?
It was the people issue.
The idea was great.
The execution of what they
actually decided to do was good.
The question is did they pick the right things?
The timing was great.
They were in the middle of an AIDS epidemic.
You know, and they had some solutions.
It was the people issue.
The co-founders had massive problems
with each other, it turned out.
They had never really worked together.
It culminated in an all night in Manhattan.
Where at the curb of the building, there were four
or five stretched limos with drivers waiting for the high,
big people on Wall Street that invested in this company.
And they spent the evening basically hashing it
out of how the company was going to work.
And at one point, one of the
big Wall Street guys got up and said,
if you guys don't figure this out, you're going to be
radioactive and you're never going to raise a dime from anyone ever.
I mean, it was that big of a moment.
They got over it.
The company eventually went public,
but it had only moderate success.
It was people issues on that one.
The final one I'm going to
talk about is I'll call NanoCo.
This was one of the first
nanotechnology companies based on quantum chemistry.
Our concepts came out of some here at MIT.
We looked at a variety of different things to do and the
product we were trying to go to market with was called NanoFuel.
We were mixing diesel fuel and water
together and running it in unmodified diesel engines.
Now you might say you
can't mix oil and water together.
Well, if you figure out
how to do that, you can't.
You can't just pour something out.
You can.
You could pour it into an unmodified diesel engine
and you got an emission profile cleaner than natural gas.
We were running it in buses at Logan Airport
for testing and in new buses and in Costa Rica.
At the time, if you wanted to get
clean transportation, people were talking about compressed natural gas.
But the energy density for
gas is much less than diesel.
And so you need to have holes.
You need to have all the
new facilities to handle the natural gas.
You needed to change buses.
The routes had to get changed.
Our stuff, all you had to
do was pour it into the tank.
We had to do some execution issues including some skunk
works because we had some disputes going on in the lab.
The lab people had their head up, I won't say where,
but timing was, and there were also other senior management issues,
but the timing was a big thing here.
When we were ready to go to
the lab, we had to get things done.
We had to get everything done.
to market, the price of diesel
fuel was at a 50-year low.
It was $0.50 a gallon at the terminal.
Wasn't that way when we started out.
I did a calculation.
And you couldn't even buy a gallon of distilled water
for $0.50.
I did a calculation that said, well,
if diesel fuel were $2 a gallon, this
would be an economically neutral type thing.
It just wasn't going to work at the time.
The company went off and did some other things,
but eventually it failed.
And every time I get behind
a big diesel truck or bus
fueling fumes, it really annoys
me that we had the solution,
but we couldn't figure out how to bring
that venture to market.
So hopefully those are some ideas.
This allows me to do one of the cheesiest animations
you're going to see.
There you go, success.
OK.
All right.
So if you get all these
things right, you get the idea right,
you get the execution, you
get the timing and the people,
you're going to have to convey
that to people in some fashion.
And so I want to spend
just a couple of minutes talking
about conveying ideas.
One of the top level things
you're going to want to do
is come up with a mission statement or a vision,
sometimes called the value proposition.
C Blank out of Stanford came
up with this version of it.
You want to.
Think about it.
It's like a zero.
Instead of a U in
the sky, just a left-wing wilayah.
It's a U in the sky.
Apparently, that's what Americans call for right across
fact check.
So let's go back to spitfield.
Say that I don't support common sense.
What I really want is I
want to go back to my ideas.
Don't blame me for my ideas.
Instead, I want to tell
you a story that I cooperated
with our co- offeners to generate易
Powell did one.
OK.
I think you can pretty much see what
they're about as a business with that statement.
So hopefully by the end of this
course, if you're actually thinking about a venture,
you might be able to do
that with something you're working on
or you'll remember this when you're looking at other things.
Now, any vision needs to be supported.
This is my famous pyramid.
I'm looking at Bob.
At the top is the mission statement.
And below that is the elevator pitch.
So each of these sort of leads to the next.
So an elevator pitch is something, you know,
the term came about back in the
days when the venture capitalists lived in,
you know, their offices were in high-rise buildings.
And you'd get in the elevator and
somebody would turn to you and say,
well, tell me what your guys are doing.
And you had the time it took that
elevator to go up to explain what it is.
And the hope after that is they would say,
well, okay.
Well, come in and tell me more.
Maybe come in or send me something.
Do you have something you
can send me, an executive summary?
Something written that could tell me about it?
And then maybe if I like that,
I'll invite you in to do a pitch
to, you know, really get into it more.
So the mission statement is, you
know, be a sentence or a paragraph.
The elevator pitch, 30 seconds.
You know, when the VCs move to low-rise buildings.
It became harder.
You had to do it quicker.
The elevators were slower, but,
you know, you still had time.
Executive summary, one, two, three, no more than four pages.
And the pitch deck, this
is Guy Kawasaki, 10, 20, 30.
Ten slides, no more.
Not more than 20 minutes
and 30-point font on the slides.
Okay, so that's, all of
that is sort of the sizzle.
So underneath that,
you need to have and understand
all of these other things to support
that distillation of what you're doing to the top.
And the stuff we're going to go through each night,
we're going to talk about
all these different things down here
to help you support the plan
you come up with, the venture idea.
Now, if you get the sizzle right,
but you don't get the support right,
you may end up like Thernos, Elizabeth Holmes.
Sentenced to prison, guilty on four of 11 charges.
She promised all this stuff.
And underneath it was, there was nothing really there.
This was fake it till you make
it, which can work in some things,
but this is medical devices.
This is, you know, blood testing.
And if you didn't diagnose somebody, people could die.
You don't want to end up here.
So most of the people here
are going to have the substance
and have a hard time with the sizzle.
But I got to caution you.
Sizzle without steak is an empty meal.
So back to our H equals R divided by E.
Well, I assume that reality was a fixed constant,
but people like Steve Jobs and maybe Elizabeth Holmes
thought you can fake it till you make it
because we can do a reality distortion field.
I wouldn't recommend it.
Does this make sense?
All right, so final, some final thoughts.
Vinod Khosla, a famous venture capitalist,
invested in a company of a friend of mine.
And my friend asked him, you know,
what advice do you have for us?
And Vinod said, you'll face a dozen real challenges
in developing the technology and venture,
which is common to most ventures.
Five of these you'll be resourceful enough
to figure out from friends, colleagues, et cetera.
All right.
You and your team are smart enough.
You'll figure those out.
My friend said, well, what about the other two?
And Vinod said, for those
two, you better get darn lucky.
Well, luck favors the well-prepared,
and we want you to be prepared.
That's the goal in this course, again,
to help you be in the part that succeeds.
if you decide to do a venture.
If you look at something
and decide it's not for you,
that's success also because you'll go find another one.
So with that, that's my overview of new ventures.
We're going to do a break
here a little early for team building.
Around the room, we've put on the walls
different interest groups that you identified
when you were signing up for the course.
I'm going to suggest you
go, if you're interested in that,
just go stand there, meet somebody,
and see if you have some interest.
And we'll come back in 10 or 15 minutes
and we'll talk about course logistics
and finding your customers.
We also have a WhatsApp
group that our TAs put together
where you can actually sign up to a WhatsApp group
and group on one of these interest things.
So we're at about 7.10.
Why don't we come back at about 7.25
and we'll talk about course logistics
and then we'll have Bob
come in and talk about customers.